PT	AU	BA	CA	GP	RI	OI	BE	Z2	TI	X1	Y1	Z1	FT	PN	AE	Z3	SO	S1	SE	BS	VL	IS	SI	MA	BP	EP	AR	DI	D2	SU	PD	PY	AB	X4	Y4	Z4	AK	CT	CY	SP	CL	TC	Z8	ZR	ZB	ZS	Z9	U1	U2	SN	EI	BN	UT	PM	J	Huntley, John Warren; Scarponi, Daniele								Evolutionary and ecological implications of trematode parasitism of modern and fossil northern Adriatic bivalves								PALEOBIOLOGY				38	1			40	51		10.1666/10051.1			WIN 2012	2012	The role of antagonistic organismal interactions in the production of long-term macroevolutionary trends has been debated for decades. Some evidence seems to suggest that temporal trends in predation frequency share a common causative mechanism with genus-level diversity, whereas studies on the role of parasites in "shaping" the evolutionary process are rare indeed. Digenean trematodes (Phylum Platyhelminthes) infest molluscs in at least one stage of their complex life cycle. Trematodes leave characteristic oval-shaped pits with raised rims on the interior of their bivalve hosts, and these pits are preserved in the fossil record. Here we survey 11,785 valves from the Pleistocene-Holocene deposits of the Po Plain and from nearby modern coastal environments on the northeast Adriatic coast of Italy. Of these, 205 valves exhibited trematode-induced pits. Trematodes were selective parasites in terms of host taxonomy and host body size. Infestation was restricted to lower shoreface/transition-to-platform paleoenvironments. During the Holocene, individuals from the transgressive systems tract were significantly more likely to be infested than those from highstand systems tracts. Temporal trends in infestation frequency cannot be explained as an ecological/evolutionary phenomenon (e.g., the hypothesis of escalation); instead the trend seems controlled by environmental variation induced by glacio-eustatic sea-level changes and inadequate sampling. Because this interaction appears to be ephemeral, both temporally and spatially, it is not likely that any selective pressure would be continuous over geologic time in this region. Furthermore, these results support the hypothesis that antagonistic interactions are lower in the northern Adriatic Sea in comparison to other midlatitude shallow marine settings.																				WOS:000299063400003		J	Fenberg, Phillip B.; Roy, Kaustuv								Anthropogenic Harvesting Pressure and Changes in Life History: Insights from a Rocky Intertidal Limpet								AMERICAN NATURALIST				180	2			200	210		10.1086/666613			AUG 2012	2012	The importance of large breeding individuals for maintaining the health of marine fish and invertebrate populations has long been recognized. Unfortunately, decades of human harvesting that preferentially remove larger individuals have led to drastic reductions in body sizes of many of these species. Such size-selective harvesting is particularly worrisome for sequentially hermaphroditic species where the larger size classes are composed primarily of one sex. Whether these species can maintain stable sex ratios under sustained harvesting pressure depends on the level of plasticity of their life-history traits. Here, we show that populations of a marine limpet (Lottia gigantea) can adjust a fundamental aspect of their life history (the timing of sex change) when subjected to size-selective harvesting. As predicted by theoretical models, individuals from harvested populations change sex at smaller sizes and grow at slower rates compared to individuals from protected populations. In addition, the relative size at which the change from male to female occurs remains constant (similar to 0.75; size at sex change/maximum size) across populations, regardless of harvesting pressure. Our results show that population-level demographic and life-history data, in conjunction with existing theory, can be sufficient to predict the responses of sequential hermaphrodites to harvesting pressure. Furthermore, they suggest such species can potentially adapt to size-selective harvesting.																				WOS:000306110300005	22766931	J	Chiba, Satoshi; Roy, Kaustuv								Selectivity of terrestrial gastropod extinctions on an oceanic archipelago and insights into the anthropogenic extinction process								PROCEEDINGS OF THE NATIONAL ACADEMY OF SCIENCES OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA				108	23			9496	9501		10.1073/pnas.1100085108			JUN 7 2011	2011	Anthropogenic impacts have led to widespread extinctions of species on oceanic islands but the nature of many of these extinctions remains poorly known. Here we investigate extinction selectivities of terrestrial gastropods from the Ogasawara archipelago in the northwest Pacific, where anthropogenic threats have changed over time, shifting primarily from the effects of habitat loss to predation by a variety of different predators. Across all of the islands, extinct species had significantly smaller geographic ranges compared with species that are still alive, but among the surviving species, ranges of those that are currently declining due to human impacts do not differ significantly from those that are not threatened. Extinctions were selective with respect to spire index (SI) of shells, a trait of potential functional importance, but the relationship between body size and extinction vulnerability varied among extinction agents, some of which were strongly size selective, whereas others were not. Overall, whereas anthropogenic impacts have resulted in nonrandom losses of phenotypic diversity, the patterns of selectivity are complex, vary among islands, and with the type of threat. As extinction agents have changed historically, so has the pattern of loss. Because of the changing nature of anthropogenic impacts, resiliency to one type of threat does not guarantee long-term survival of species and future patterns of biodiversity loss on these islands are likely to be different from those in the past.																				WOS:000291341400039	21606352	J	Jimenez, Andrea; Rennie, Michael D.; Sprules, W. Gary; La Rose, Jake								Temporal changes in the benthic invertebrate community of Lake Simcoe, 1983-2008								JOURNAL OF GREAT LAKES RESEARCH				37		SI		103	112		10.1016/j.jglr.2010.07.002		3	2011	2011	The Lake Simcoe ecosystem has been subjected to multiple stressors during the past century, including changes in nutrient loads and the introduction of non-native species. To evaluate the effects of these changes on the Lake Simcoe offshore benthic community, we collected benthic samples in 2008 at sites allowing statistical comparisons with detailed surveys in 1983 and qualitative comparisons with others focussing more on nearshore collections in 2005 and 1926. Total abundance of benthic invertebrates declined significantly from 1983 to 2008, and correspondence analyses revealed major changes in community composition. Typical of the overall pattern, three of the major benthic taxa (Nematoda, Oligochaeta and Ostracoda) declined from 1983 to 2008, particularly at depths greater than 10 m. Chironomids showed little change in abundance from 1983 to 2008 but their biomass increased because body length nearly doubled during this period. Oligochaete abundance declined but biomass remained the same due to increases in body length from 1983 to 2008. Ostracod abundance and biomass both declined because body size distributions did not change from 1983 to 2008. In contrast to total invertebrate abundance, that of dreissenid mussels, amphipods, isopods, gastropods and sphaeriids increased and these taxa also occupied greater depths (up to 30 m) in 2008 compared with historical surveys. Our results suggest a strong effect of both water quality changes and dreissenid establishment in shaping the contemporary Lake Simcoe benthic invertebrate community. (C) 2010 International Association for Great Lakes Research. Published by Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.																				WOS:000291713100012		J	Huang, Wen-Bin; Hseu, Jinn-Rong								Changes in growth characteristics of the small abalone Haliotis diversicolor (Reeve, 1846) after one decade in a closed culture system: a comparison with wild populations								FISHERIES SCIENCE				76	1			131	137		10.1007/s12562-009-0190-1			JAN 2010	2010	Small abalone Haliotis diversicolor (Reeve, 1846) is one of the smallest commercial abalone in the world. The successful application of artificial propagation and mass seed production techniques since the 1980s have resulted in the establishment of well-developed culture systems for small abalone in Taiwan. In the study reported here, we estimated the growth of a population of small abalone after a decade in a closed culture system and its growth characteristics with those of wild populations reported in previous studies. The von Bertalanffy growth equations of the shell length (L) and body weight (W) of cultured abalone were L (t) = 71.73 (1 - e(-0.84 (t-0.16))) and W (t) = 47.70 (1 - e(-0.84 (t-0.16)))(3.180), respectively. The instantaneous rate of change for weight had an inflection point at the age of 1.54 years, indicating that cultured abalones reach their apex of body growth around this age. Compared with the wild populations, the cultured population exhibits a significantly smaller maximal shell length (L (a)) and a significantly larger growth coefficient (k). Based on our results, it appears that the artificial culture of generations of small albalone for one decade or more in a closed system could be one of the major factors causing the observed minimization of size in the cultured abalone; this may be an adaptation in which growth is traded off for the larger k.																				WOS:000273102000014		J	de Kock, K. N.; Wolmarans, C. T.								Distribution of the indigenous clam Pisidium costulosum Connolly 1931 (Bivalvia: Sphaeriidae) in relation to temperature, rainfall and watertype in South Africa				Verspreiding van die inheemse mossel Pisidium costulosum Connolly 1931 (Bivalvia: Sphaeriidae) met betrekking tot temperatuur, reenval en watertipe in Suid-Afrika				Suid-Afrikaanse Tydskrif vir Natuurwetenskap en Tegnologie				28	4			399	413					DEC 2009	2009	Distribution of the indigenous clam Pisidium costulosum Connolly 1931 (Bivalvia:Sphaeriidae) in relation to temperature, rainfall and watertype in South AfricaLittle is known of the junctional role of freshwater bivalves and particularly the ecology of burrowing species has been inadequately studied. This is an unfortunate situation in view of the fact that freshwater biotopes are losing biodiversily at an alarming rate. The genus Pisidium includes some of the tiniest bivalve species known to man, it has a worldwide distribution and its origin is considered to be Mesozoic. Due to the fact that Pisidium can exploit virtually almost any freshwater habitat, that it is a bottom dweller and filter feeder and is also relatively long lived, it is important to study species of this genus because they could be used for monitoring environmental conditions. This article focuses on the geographical distribution and habitats Of P. costulosum, a species considered to be endemic to South Africa and which is the most widespread of the six Pisidium species on record for this country in the database of the National Freshwater Snail Collection (NFSC).Details pertaining to the habitats of the 428 samples of P. costulosum as recorded at the time of collection were extracted from the database of the NFSC. The 187 loci (1/16 th square degrees) in which the 428 collection sites were located, were distributed in pre-selected intervals of mean annual air temperature and rainfall, as well as intervals of mean altitude, to illustrate the frequency of occurrence within specific intervals. A temperature index was calculated for all mollusc species in the database from their frequencies of occurrence within the selected intervals and the results used to rank them in order of their association with low to high climatic temperatures. To evaluate the significance of the difference between frequencies of occurrence in, on, or at the various options for each parameter investigated, chi-square values were calculated. In addition an effect size value was calculated to determine the contribution of each parameter towards establishing the geographical distribution of this species based on the data in the database. A multivariate analysis in the form of a decision tree was also constructed from the data which enabled the selection and ranking of those variables that maximally discriminated between the frequency of occurrence of P. costulosum in, on, or at the various options for each parameter as compared to all other bivalve species in the database.Our records show that this species is well represented in Gauteng and the central and southern areas of Mpumalanga. It is relatively continuously spread through the north eastern parts of the Free State and all along its eastern and southern borders, sparsely distributed in the Northern Cape and poorly represented in Limpopo.Although it was reported from 13 of the 14 water-bodies represented in the database, more than 60% of the samples were recovered from streams and rivers and from water conditions described as perennial, standing, clear and fresh and more than 45% came from habitats with a predominantly muddy substratum.From the effect size values calculated for the various parameters it can be deduced that type of water-body, temperature and altitude played the most significant role in establishing the geographical distribution of this species in South Africa.On account of the fact that country-wide surveys by government and local health authorities were discontinued in the early 1980 the current range of the geographical distribution of freshwater mollusc species in South Africa is rather uncertain. The data in the database were compiled over a period of approximately five decades and due to the fact that the majority of sampling sites have not been revisited since, little is known of the conservation status of the freshwater molluscs of South Africa. Its close association with cooler climatic conditions as indicated by its temperature index and its dependency on perennial habitats, suggest that P. costulosum could be vulnerable to climatic changes due to global warming and that this could have a negative impact on the range of its geographical distribution. It is suggested that efforts should be made to update the geographical distribution of at least those mollusc species that are of medical and veterinary importance and at the same time to monitor the progress of exotic mollusc species in their invasion of water-bodies in this country. A comparison of the results of such surveys with the long range of data in the NFSC database could be valuable to assess the current conservation status of at least some of the indigenous freshwater molluscs of this country.																				BCI:BCI201000124328		J	Grabowska, Joanna; Grabowski, Michal; Kostecka, Anna								Diet and feeding habits of monkey goby (Neogobius fluviatilis) in a newly invaded area								BIOLOGICAL INVASIONS				11	9			2161	2170		10.1007/s10530-009-9499-z			NOV 2009	2009	The monkey goby (Neogobius fluviatilis) is one of the Ponto-Caspian species that in recent decades made substantial East-to-West invasions in European inland waters. Now the species is present in the Danube as far as its Slovakian section. In the last decade the species also invaded the Western Bug and Vistula rivers, in the latter it is numerous nearly as far as its delta. The purpose of our study was to define the diet spectrum, feeding preferences, spatial and size related changes in diet and diurnal feeding activity of this goby. Another goal was to predict which groups of native prey would be most affected by the presence of this exotic predator in newly invaded areas. The study was carried out at three sampling locations in the Vistula River system. The food spectrum of the monkey goby was broad. The fish consumed insect larvae and pupae, crustaceans, annelids, gastropods and fish. Chironomid larvae were a prevalent food category in all sampling sites, followed by amphipod crustaceans at one site and by trichopteran larvae and chironomid pupae at another. At the third site, there was no distinct subdominant food category. According to the values of the Ivlev's selectivity index, the preferred food category were chironomid larvae. No significant differences in diet were found over the 24-h cycle. There was no variation among different fish size groups. From our studies and from the available literature data it can be concluded that the species, due to its ability to use locally available food resources, displays a generalistic and highly flexible feeding strategy.					15th International Conference on Aquatic Invasive Species (ICAIS)15th International Conference on Aquatic Invasive Species (ICAIS)	SEP 23-27, 2007SEP 23-27, 2007		Nijmegen, NETHERLANDSNijmegen, NETHERLANDS												WOS:000270646300015		J	Fisher, Jonathan A. D.; Rhile, Erika C.; Liu, Harrison; Petraitis, Peter S.								An intertidal snail shows a dramatic size increase over the past century								PROCEEDINGS OF THE NATIONAL ACADEMY OF SCIENCES OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA				106	13			5209	5212		10.1073/pnas.0812137106			MAR 31 2009	2009	Changes in the shell architecture of marine snails enhance defenses and greatly improve survival against predators. In the northwest Atlantic Ocean, shorter and thicker shells have been reported for several species following the introduction of predatory Carcinus maenas crabs early in the 20th century. But we report that the shell lengths of Nucella lapillus actually increased by an average of 22.6% over the past century, with no evidence of shell thickening after correcting for shell length. The increases in shell length were greatest on sheltered shores, highlighting the interaction between wave exposure and the sampling period. Comparisons were based on archived shells collected in 1915-1922 from sites that were resampled in 2007. N. lapillus is an important member of North Atlantic marine ecosystems, and our results suggest that the impacts of historical changes in species' key morphological traits on marine ecosystems remain underappreciated.																				WOS:000264790600047	19307561	J	Pittman, Simon J.; Hile, Sarah D.; Jeffrey, Christopher F.G.; Caldow, Chris; Kendall, Matt S.; Monaco, Mark E.; Hillis-Starr, Zandy								Fish assemblages and benthic habitats of Buck Island Reef National Monument (St. Croix, U.S. Virgin Islands) and the surrounding seascape: a characterization of spatial and temporal patterns.								NOAA Technical Memorandum NOS NCCOS				71				i	xvi, 1-80					May 2008	2008	Since 1999, NOAA's Biogeography Branch of the Center for Coastal Monitoring and Assessment (CCMA-BB) has been working with federal and territorial partners to characterize, monitor, and assess the status of the marine environment around northeastern St. Croix, U.S. Virgin Islands. This effort is part of the broader NOAA Coral Reef Conservation Program's (CRCP) National Coral Reef Ecosystem Monitoring Program (NCREMP). With support from CRCP's NCREMP, CCMA conducts the "Caribbean Coral Reef Ecosystem Monitoring project" (CREM) with goals to: (1) spatially characterize and monitor the distribution, abundance, and size of marine fauna associated with shallow water coral reef seascapes (mosaics of coral reefs, seagrasses, sand and mangroves); (2) relate this information to in situ ine-scale habitat data and the spatial distribution and diversity of habitat types using benthic habitat maps; (3) use this information to establish the knowledge base necessary for enacting management decisions in a spatial setting; (4) establish the eficacy of those management decisions; and (5) develop data collection and data management protocols. The monitoring effort in northeastern St. Croix was conducted through partnerships with the National Park Service (NPS) and the Virgin Islands Department of Planning and Natural Resources (VI-DPNR). The geographical focal point of the research is Buck Island Reef National Monument (BIRNM), a protected area originally established in 1961 and greatly expanded in 2001; however, the work also encompassed a large portion of the recently created St. Croix East End Marine Park (EEMP). Project funding is primarily provided by NOAA CRCP, CCMA and NPS. In recent decades, scientiic and non-scientiic observations have indicated that the structure and function of the coral reef ecosystem around northeastern St. Croix have been adversely impacted by a wide range of environmental stressors. The major stressors have included the mass Diadema die off in the early 1980s, a series of hurricanes beginning with Hurricane Hugo in 1989, overishing, mass mortality of Acropora corals due to disease and several coral bleaching events, with the most severe mass bleaching episode in 2005. The area is also an important recreational resource supporting boating, snorkeling, diving and other water based activities. With so many potential threats to the marine ecosystem and a dramatic change in management strategy in 2003 when the park's Interim Regulations (Presidential Proclamation No. 7392) established BIRNM as one of the irst fully protected marine areas in NPS system, it became critical to identify existing marine fauna and their spatial distributions and temporal dynamics. This provides ecologically meaningful data to assess ecosystem condition, support decision making in spatial planning (including the evaluation of eficacy of current management strategies) and determine future information needs. The ultimate goal of the work is to better understand the coral reef ecosystems and to provide information toward protecting and enhancing coral reef ecosystems for the beneit of the system itself and to sustain the many goods and services that it offers society. This Technical Memorandum contains analysis of the first six years of fish survey data (2001-2006) and associated characterization of the benthos (1999-2006). The primary objectives were to quantify changes in ish species and assemblage diversity, abundance, biomass and size structure and to provide spatially explicit information on the distribution of key species or groups of species and to compare community structure inside (protected) versus outside (ished) areas of BIRNM. Methods: For each biannual survey mission, selection of sample sites occurred via a stratiied random design (2001-2006) using hard and soft bottom habitat types delineated in NOAA's benthic habitat map (Menza et al., 2006). In 2003, after implementation of the park's Interim Regulations, sampling was also stratiied by whether or not the site was located inside or outside BIRNM to evaluate effect of the ishing closure (only 2003 to 2006). Fish were surveyed during daylight hours along 25 m long by 4 m wide belt-transects for a ixed duration of 15 minutes. All species observed were identified to the lowest possible taxonomic level and their abundance was counted and grouped by size class. To quantify benthic habitat, ive 1 m2 quadrats were randomly placed on the transect and used to examine the relatively fine-scale biotic and abiotic components of the seascape (e.g., coral cover, macroalgal cover, etc.). In addition, Geographical Information System (GIS) tools were used to quantify the seascape surrounding each transect using habitat distributions represented in NOAA's benthic habitat maps (e.g., amount of seagrass, number of habitat types, etc.). Comparative analyses of biotic components inside versus outside BIRNM were conducted using a wide range of ish variables representing community, trophic, family and individual species level data incorporating measures of abundance, biomass and diversity. A total of 884 transects collected between 2003 and 2006 inclusively were used to examine differences in ish metrics inside versus outside BIRNM. Benthic comparisons used 716 benthic surveys on hardbottom habitat types conducted between 2001 and 2006. Abundance maps were used to examine species distributions for both juveniles and adults and interpolations of point data were used to examine broad-scale spatial patterns of ish and benthic habitat variables. Major indings: Diversity hotspots [center dot] Despite heavy impacts from disease, bleaching and hurricanes, the area around the eastern tip of Buck Island remains ecologically distinctive having some of the highest live coral cover and rugosity in the mapped region, also with high calcareous coralline algal cover, high ish species richness, biomass of herbivorous ish and high abundance for many common ish species.[center dot] The linear reef (i.e., barrier reefs) and adjacent colonized pavement that extends east-west from Teague Bay to Coakley Bay and now falls within the EEMP "no-take zone" and "recreation zone" was found to support high coral species richness and fish species richness. [center dot] Extensive areas with high coral species richness, high live coral cover for Montastraea cavernosa and M. annularis, high ish species richness and high abundance for several ish species including coney (Cephalopholis fulva), rock beauty (Holacanthus tricolor) and queen triggerish (Balistes vetula) occurred along the northernmost edge of the benthic habitat map. This indicates that important deeper water habitat is likely to exist beyond the scope of this report, requiring further benthic habitat mapping effort combined with visual census (diver/remotely operated vehicle [ROV]) to capture data on ish communities (see Foster Mission web site: http://ccma.nos.noaa.gov/products/biogeography/ usvi_nps/overview.htm). [center dot] Many of the coral reefs with highest ish species richness were within 200 m of seagrass beds. Several other studies have demonstrated links between ish distribution on coral reefs and proximity to seagrass beds suggesting that many species may beneit from complementary resources provided by seagrasses in close proximity to coral reefs. This highlights the importance of considering mosaics of habitat types in resource management decision making. Benthic habitat [center dot] The benthic environment inside BIRNM was signiicantly different to the outside for 75% of ine-scale variables quantiied within 1 m2 quadrates and 78% of seascape variables quantiied within 100 m2 radius seascape units surrounding each transect. [center dot] Seventy-eight percent of the mapped area inside BIRNM was hardbottom habitat dominated by colonized pavement and 22% was softbottom (sand and seagrasses); outside BIRNM, 46% was hardbottom and 54% softbottom. Seascapes inside BIRNM also had signiicantly higher mean habitat richness. [center dot] Coral cover for all major scleractinian (hard coral) families was signiicantly higher inside BIRNM and coral reefs had a signiicantly higher ratio of live coral cover to macroalgal cover than outside BIRNM. [center dot] Overall, hardbottom habitats of the study area were dominated by turf algae (37%) and macroalgae (11.4%), with mean scleractinian coral cover of only 5.6% ranging from 12.1% on patch reefs to 2% on the less rugose reef rubble. [center dot] Across years (2003-2006), macroalgal cover showed some indication of decline both inside and outside BIRNM. [center dot] Filamentous cyanobacteria/macroalgal blooms were detected in the fall sampling period with mean cover as high as 18% in October 2005; a year with anomalously high summer water temperatures that also resulted in a mass coral bleaching event. [center dot] Peaks in mean algal turf cover (50-60%) were detected in the spring (2006) season following the mass coral bleaching event and mean live coral cover approximately one year after the event was the lowest since this study commenced. Fish [center dot] A total of 201 ish species/species groups were identified from 56 families. Nine of the 10 most frequently encountered species belonged to the families Labridae (wrasse), Acanthuridae (surgeonish) and Scaridae (parrotish). [center dot] The majority of the most abundant ish across the study region were found in highest densities over hardbottom habitat types, yet most also utilized multiple habitat types including seagrasses and sand. [center dot] Fish metrics signiicantly higher on hardbottom habitat inside BIRNM included ish biomass (all ish combined), herbivore biomass, parrotish biomass, shark and ray biomass, coney (C. fulva) density and biomass, blue tang (Acanthurus coeruleus) density and biomass, and striped parrotish (Scarus iseri) biomass. [center dot] Fish metrics signiicantly higher outside BIRNM included ecologically important predator groups such as piscivore biomass (including sharks and rays), snapper (Lutjanidae) density, and grunt (Haemulidae) density and biomass. [center dot] Red hind (Epinephelus guttatus) and coney (C. fulva) exhibited distinct patterns in spatial distributions, with high coney density mostly over the contiguous colonized hardbottom areas (much of which is inside BIRNM) and high densities of red hind found mostly to the south of Buck Island (many outside BIRNM). [center dot] Very few of the largest (>35 cm) and very few of the smallest (<5 cm) size classes were observed for groupers (Serranidae) and snappers. Groupers and snappers in the largest size class (>35 cm) were recorded at <1% and 3%, of survey sites, respectively. [center dot] Body lengths of the largest individuals of several common groupers, snappers and grunts were less than the maximum size recorded for the species. The largest yellowtail snapper (Ocyurus chrysurus) was approximately 70% of the maximum known adult size, schoolmaster snapper (Lutjanus apodus) 66%, bluestriped grunt (Haemulon sciurus) 65- 76%, white grunt (H. plumierii) 56-66% and red hind (E. guttatus) 60% of known maximum size. [center dot] Highest densities of threespot damselish (Stegastes planifrons), a potential indicator of healthy reefs with high live coral cover, were found around the eastern tip of Buck Island within BIRNM and the fringing reef extending east-west along the northeast coast of St. Croix.Historic and recent changes in ish populations [center dot] Synoptic overview of inter-annual differences inside and outside BIRNM showed no consistent decline for any of the 39 ish metrics inside BIRNM, but instead showed increases every year between 2003 and 2006 for mean ish density (all species combined). Densities in 2005 and 2006 were signiicantly higher than 2003. It is not yet clear if this has resulted from initiation of NPS Interim Regulations and enforcement patrols. [center dot] No such increases were recorded outside BIRNM, instead considerable and consecutive inter-annual decline was apparent for grunt biomass, especially bluestriped grunt (H. sciurus), and density and biomass of stripped parrotish (S. iseri). Densities in 2005 and 2006 were significantly lower than 2003. [center dot] Only three Nassau grouper (Epinephelus striatus), three yellowin grouper (Mycteroperca venenosa) and one tiger grouper (M. tigris) were observed in the study region over the course of six years of monitoring using 1,275 samples. Notably, these three species were completely absent from the Buck Island nearshore areas in 2001-2006, but were present in low abundance in 1979. These grouper species are highly vulnerable to ishing due to their large body size and relatively slow maturity and this historical difference in abundance indicates that the grouper have been overished. [center dot] In contrast, coney (C. fulva) and red hind (E. guttatus) were more abundant around Buck Island between 2001 and 2006 than in 1979. [center dot] Threespot damselish (S. planifrons), a potential indicator of healthy reefs with high live coral cover, was more abundant around Buck Island in 1979 than in the 2001-2006 sampling period. Macroinvertebrates [center dot] Long-spined urchin densities (Diadema antillarum) around Buck Island have not recovered since the mass mortality in 1983. However, this study and the scientiic literature indicate that some minor recovery may be occurring in lagoonal and back reef areas along the sheltered coastline of northeastern St. Croix. Long-spined urchins were once important ecosystem engineers controlling the abundance of algae in the region and little is known about the factors (e.g, limitations to recruitment) that are controlling population recovery. [center dot] Coral reef ecosystems of the study region, particularly the large expanse of seagrasses between Buck Island and St. Croix support regionally important populations of adult and juvenile queen conch (Strombus gigas). This is important since queen conch is an important food resource in the Virgin Islands and according to NOAA's Ofice of Protected Species, queen conch is declining throughout the species' range. Recommendations: Additional mapping, inventory and monitoring efforts are required to explore the deeper water ecosystems within the BIRNM that exist outside NOAA's current benthic habitat map. In addition, acoustic tracking studies may reveal the mechanisms underlying some of the observed temporal changes in fish communities and will determine connectivity between lagoons and coral reefs offshore. Tracking will also provide important information on the time that individual ish spend inside and outside the boundaries of protected areas. Very little is known about the timing of movements during the daily home range, ontogenetic shifts and spawning migrations and spatial pathways for such movements for most species. Some targeted surveying for specific substrate types may be required to identify the extent of suitable settlement habitat for juvenile grouper in the study region or whether groupers are instead immigrating into the region from settlement habitat outside. Long-term monitoring is necessary to determine the magnitude of the apparent declines and to track the trajectory of recovery for species that exhibited an increase in density after several years of decline. Long-term monitoring effort may also reveal direction in the change for the many species that were too highly variable from year to year to provide such information over the four years of data used. Within the BIRNM-EEMP Marine Protected Area (MPA) complex, resource managers and stakeholders should examine the option of closing the gap between the southern boundary of BIRNM and the no-take zone of EEMP along the northeastern coast of St. Croix. An adjoining of the boundaries would incorporate an extensive area of seagrass habitat thus ensuring full protection of important complementary resources that provide food and habitat for many ish (both resident and transient species). These seagrass beds are also regionally important habitat for queen conch and may provide important resources for Caribbean spiny lobster. Further targeted surveys are required to assess and monitor the status of queen conch populations and to determine whether long-spined urchins are recovering. Such information will help to determine if management intervention is needed to assist recovery of sea urchin populations and to evaluate the conch ishery. Additional work to map the distribution of juvenile and adult Caribbean spiny lobster populations using existing survey data and to determine the factors that explain spatial distributions would be very valuable in supporting ecosystem-based management of marine resources in the region. Benthic habitat maps should be periodically updated due to the dynamic nature of coral reef ecosystems. This is particularly important when linking ish seascape structure and when assessing seascape change such as quantifying gain or loss of major habitat types.																				ZOOREC:ZOOR14608054819		J	Brookes, J. I.; Rochette, Remy								Mechanism of a plastic phenotypic response: predator-induced shell thickening in the intertidal gastropod Littorina obtusata								JOURNAL OF EVOLUTIONARY BIOLOGY				20	3			1015	1027		10.1111/j.1420-9101.2007.01299.x			MAY 2007	2007	Phenotypic plasticity has been the object of considerable interest over the past several decades, but in few cases are mechanisms underlying plastic responses well understood. For example, it is unclear whether predator-induced changes in gastropod shell morphology represent an active physiological response or a by-product of reduced feeding. We address this question by manipulating feeding and growth of intertidal snails, Littorina obtusata, using two approaches: (i) exposure to predation cues from green crabs Carcinus maenas and (ii) reduced food availability, and quantifying growth in shell length, shell mass, and body mass, as well as production of faecal material and shell micro-structural characteristics (mineralogy and organic fraction) after 96 days. We demonstrate that L. obtusata actively increases calcification rate in response to predation threat, and that this response entails energetic and developmental costs. That this induced response is not strictly tied to the animal's behaviour should enhance its evolutionary potential.																				WOS:000245989600019	17465912	J	Mieszkowska, N.; Hawkins, S. J.; Burrows, M. T.; Kendall, M. A.								Long-term changes in the geographic distribution and population structures of Osilinus lineatus (Gastropoda : Trochidae) in Britain and Ireland								JOURNAL OF THE MARINE BIOLOGICAL ASSOCIATION OF THE UNITED KINGDOM				87	2			537	545		10.1017/S0025315407053799			APR 2007	2007	Since the rate of global climate change began to accelerate in the 1980s, the coastal seas of Britain have warmed by tip to l degrees C. Locations close to the northern range edges of a southern trochid gastropod Osilinus lineatus in Britain previously surveyed in the 1950s and 1980s were resurveyed during 2002-2004 to determine whether changes in the success of near-limit populations had occurred during the period of climate warming. Between the 1980s and the 2000s, the range limits had extended by up to 55 krn. Populations sampled over a latitudinal extent of 4 degrees from northern limits towards the centre of the range showed synchronous increases in abundance throughout the years sampled, suggesting a large-scale factor such as climate was driving the observed changes. These increases in abundance and changes in range limits are likely to have occurred via increased recruitment success in recent years.																				WOS:000246419200022		J	Lindeman, PV								Diet of the Texas map turtle (Graptemys versa): Relationship to sexually dimorphic trophic morphology and changes over five decades as influenced by an invasive mollusk								CHELONIAN CONSERVATION AND BIOLOGY				5	1			25	31					MAY 2006	2006	The diet of the Texas map turtle (Graptemys versa) in the Colorado River drainage was studied using 1) stomach flushing and collection of feces in 1998-1999 and 2) dissection of museum specimens collected in 1949 prior to invasion of their habitats by exotic Asian clams (Corbicula spp.). Feces were found to be better indicators of dietary diversity based on log-log comparisons of sample volume with turtle size and the fact that Corbicula were absent in stomach flushes of small female specimens that yielded abundant shell fragments in their feces. Adult males fed most heavily on aquatic insect larvae (primarily trichopterans and ephemeropterans) and showed little change in diet over 5 decades. Small females that overlapped adult males in body size had wider heads and alveolar surfaces of the jaws than did males and fed predominantly on Corbicula, snails, insect larvae, and algae. Females that were larger than males in body size showed a change from a diverse diet in 1949 that included sphaeriid clams, trichopteran larvae, sponges, bryozoans, and algae, to nearly exclusive feeding on the invasive mollusk Corbicala 5 decades later. Based on the present report and previous studies, it appears that I result of the invasion of rivers in North America by Corbicula is greatly decreased diversity of diet in adult female Graptemys of moderate head width (mesocephaly).																				WOS:000237796000005		J	Marui, Y; Chiba, S; Okuno, J; Yamasaki, K								Species-area curve for land snails on Kikai Island in geological time								PALEOBIOLOGY				30	2			222	230		10.1666/0094-8373(2004)030<0222:SCFLSO>2.0.CO;2			SPR 2004	2004	Historical changes in the coastline of Kikai Island of the Ryukyu Islands in the southeast part of Japan were estimated by using a numerical simulation based on a glacio-hydro-isostasy model. Temporal changes in the area of the island during the last 40 Kyr were compared with temporal changes in species diversity in fossil land snails of the island. The species number in the past was theoretically estimated by the area of Kikai Island in the past and a species-area relationship among the modern land snail fauna of the Ryukyu Islands. The theoretical species numbers are very close to the actual ones. This suggests that the change in island area is the main cause of the change in species diversity in Kikai Island. In addition, we discuss causes other than the area, such as island elevation, distance to the nearest large island, climate change, human activity, and imperfection of fossil data. We also discuss the change in Fisher's alpha and body size against the change in the area.																				WOS:000221075400004		J	Richling, I								Classification of the Helicinidae: Review of morphological characteristics based on a revision of the Costa Rican species and application to the arrangement of the Central American mainland taxa (Mollusca : Gastropoda : Neritopsina)								MALACOLOGIA				45	2			195	440					2004	2004	The present study combines a taxonomical revision of the poorly known Costa Rican Helicinidae, with a detailed investigation of certain morphological structures with respect to their relevance for systematics, culminating in a discussion of the arrangement of the Central American mainland species.The revision of the Costa Rican species is based on the examination of nearly all type material, coupled with extensive field work and investigations of the collections of the Instituto Nacional de Biodiversidad de Costa Rica and the Florida Museum of Natural History, Gainesville, along with perusal of additional historical material. With minor exceptions, all these species were investigated with respect to the features of shell, operculum, surface sculpture of embryonic shell and teleoconch, internal shell structures, radula, and female reproductive system. In addition, analyses of morphometry and sexual dimorphism were carried out. Faced with a limited amount of material, it became necessary to develop a new preparation method to separate the soft body from the shell without damaging either.For the higher classification and comparative analysis of the different morphological characteristics, similar examinations emphasizing formerly poorly studied or neglected characteristics, such as embryonic shell and female reproductive system, were carried out for 17 additional species representing the most important related Central American supraspecific taxa using their type species when available. For taxa with inaccessible material, data from the available literature were critically incorporated.For Costa Rica, 15 species were recognized, among them seven new species, partially published in Richling (2001) - Helicina echandiensis, H. talamancensis, H. monteverdensis, H. chiquitica, H. escondida, Alcadia (Microalcadia) hojarasca, and A. (M.) boeckeleri - and two new subspecies - H. punctisulcata cuericiensis, and H. beatrix dopejensis. Other previously subspecifically separated taxa (H. funcki costaricensis Wagner, 1905; H. tenuis pittieri Wagner, 1910) were shown to fall within the range of intraspecific variability. Records of the Guatemalan and Mexican species Helicina oweniana L. Pfeiffer, 1849, and subspecies, H. amoena L. Pfeiffer, 1849, as well as those of H. fragilis Morelet, 1851, were proven to be based on faulty identifications and were therefore excluded from the Costa Rican fauna. This fact, together with the recognition of the several new species, shows that the faunal composition of Costa Rica is much more distinct from that of the northern areas than previously assumed. The transitional zone of Nicaragua, however, still remains widely uninvestigated. Only Helicina tenuis L. Pfeiffer, 1849, being ecologically very tolerant, Lucidella lirata (L. Pfeiffer, 1847), and Pyrgodomus microdinus (Morelet, 1851) are widespread, extending from Mexico to Costa Rica, perhaps even farther south. The distribution of the typical Costa Rican species follows the topographical subdivision created by the Central Cordilleras, along with its corresponding effects on the climate.Contrary to former assumptions, certain features of the female reproductive system proved very useful for the classification of the Helicinidae. For the first time, monaulic conditions have been recognized for Helicina and Eutrochatella, necessitating the correction of previous descriptions in this respect. Furthermore, the monaulic or diaulic state is characteristic of the genera and is paralleled by consistent changes in the embryonic shell structure. Because primitive members of the Helicinidae possess a diaulic system, the monaulic condition is regarded as the derived state. The Central American genera Helicina, Alcadia, Eutrochatella, Lucidella and Schasicheila were properly distinguished and described by this, as well as by other differences in the female reproductive system. The anatomies of the type species of Helicina and Alcadia were examined for the first time, and earlier descriptions of Eutrochatella and Lucidella were corrected in major points. On the basis of this new evidence, the assignment of traditional subgeneric units of Helicina and Alcadia, previously based mainly on vague radula and shell characteristics, was especially reassessed. The subgenera Sericea and Analcadia were transferred to Helicina, as well as the mainland land species summarized under the preoccupied taxon "Gemma". Tristramia, Oxyrhombus, Pseudoligyra, Oligyra, Succincta, "Cinctella" [also preoccupied] and Punctisulcata were confirmed in their association with Helicina. Due to its monaulic condition, the former genus Ceochasma is reduced to a subgenus of Helicina. In addition, exemplary non-type Antillean species were studied, including Helicina jamaicensis Sowerby, 1841, which had to be shifted to Alcadia s.l., and Alcadia (Analcadia) platychila (von Muhlfedt, 1816), which is now assigned to Helicina s.s. On one hand, the new arrangement excludes Alcadia as previously known from the Central American mainland, but, on the other hand, examination of the newly discovered Costa Rican species Helicina hojarasca and H. boeckeleri required the establishment of a new subgenus of Alcadia, Microalcadia n. subgen. on the mainland, based mainly on the features of the female reproductive system and embryonic shell structure. The occurrence of Alcadia with only a few diminutive species on the mainland of Central America corresponds to the distribution of the genera Eutrochatella/Pyrgodomus and Lucidella.The Central American mainland species of Helicina seem to show a closer relationship among each other than to the northern South American subgenera Analcadia and Sericea. The Brazilian taxon Angulata, previously a subgroup of Helicina, deviates remarkably in embryonic shell structure and shows differences in anatomy that still require final confirmation, and it thus deserves recognition as a separate genus.Contrary to the well-supported differentiation at the generic level, the attempt to characterize subgroups of the Central American mainland species of Helicina has been only partially successful. Certain similarities in teleoconch surface structure, relative development of the accessory structures of the female reproductive system, and the degree of sexual dimorphism become obvious and are discussed to some extent, but intermediate characteristics complicate a satisfactory solution. Besides Ceochasma, three Central American mainland subgenera are recognized: Oligyra, Tristramia most closely resembling Helicina s.s., and "Gemma". The latter preoccupied name is tentatively retained, because the proposal of a new name seems inappropriate at this stage.Investigation of the morphological features other than the embryonic shell sculpture and the female reproductive system revealed the following additional results, mainly based on the Costa Rican species of Helicina:Characteristics of teleoconch, operculum, and radula, previously regarded as substantial for classification, were repeatedly demonstrated to be subject to convergent development, thus limiting their value for systematics. Different examples are given, such as the T-shaped lateral of the radula or periostracal hairs, and further evidence is provided by the necessary re-arrangements outlined above. Nevertheless, these features play a supplementary or supporting role.The mantle pigmentation of arboreal Helicinidae is closely related to the transparency of the shell and functionally replaces shell color in thin shells. The physiological possibility of an obviously adaptable mantle pigmentation could provide the opportunity for survival with thin, transparent shells as adaptation to the limited availability of calcium carbonate. Whereas varying and patterned mantle color are characteristic for arboreal thin-shelled species, the color of the head and foot is seldom species specific.Size differences of the embryonic shell have not previously been studied for Helicinidae. Embryonic shell size is shown to increase with the shell size within a group of related species and also altitude within different populations of a species. Furthermore, it may show a certain species specificity. Preliminary data on Lucidella and Eutrochatella/Pyrgodomus suggest a consistently smaller embryonic shell size than in Helicina or Alcadia.Internal shell structures-axial cleft and muscle attachments-seem characteristic for certain systematic units, for example, Lucidella and Schasicheila. The length of the axial cleft is confirmed to be constant within a species, but, contrary to former assumption, it is not related to the whorl count.The data on sexual dimorphism given in this study represent the most comprehensive approach to date to analyze this phenomenon for Helicinidae. The sexual dimorphism may manifest itself in differences in volume, a male's size being only about 62-70% of that of the female's, but formerly assumed deviations in shape could not be proved to be of significance for species of Helicina. A certain value for the degree of differences in uncovering systematic affinities is indicated.																				WOS:000220331200001		J	Roy, K; Collins, AG; Becker, BJ; Begovic, E; Engle, JM								Anthropogenic impacts and historical decline in body size of rocky intertidal gastropods in southern California								ECOLOGY LETTERS				6	3			205	211		10.1046/j.1461-0248.2003.00419.x			MAR 2003	2003	The diverse fauna and flora of rocky intertidal ecosystems are being impacted by the activities of rapidly increasing coastal populations in many regions of the world. Human harvesting of intertidal species can lead to significant changes in body sizes of these taxa. However, little is known about the temporal trajectories of such size declines and more importantly, the long-term effects of chronic human impacts. Furthermore, it is unclear whether sizes of species not directly targeted for harvesting are also declining through indirect effects. Here we use historical (extending back to 1869) and field survey data covering 200 km of mainland southern California coast to show that human activities have led to significant and widespread declines in body sizes of rocky intertidal gastropod species over the last century. These declines, initiated several decades ago, are continuing and contrary to expectation, they are not restricted to species harvested for human consumption. Data from the only national park in this area, where conservation laws are strictly imposed, demonstrate that negative ecological impacts can be ameliorated if existing laws are enforced.																				WOS:000181272100008		J	Trussell, GC; Nicklin, MO								Cue sensitivity, inducible defense, and trade-offs in a marine snail								ECOLOGY				83	6			1635	1647		10.2307/3071984			JUN 2002	2002	Despite considerable progress in the study of inducible defenses, our understanding of the role of cues and costs to their ecology and evolution remains limited. This study, focused on inducible defenses in the intertidal snail, Littorina obtusata, in response to the invasive green crab, Carcinus maenas, in the Gulf of Maine. We used widely separated (similar to400 km) snail populations from northern Maine and Massachusetts because they differ in their extent of historical and present-day contact with C. maenas. Crabs are presently more abundant in the southern Gulf and have been there for twice as long (similar to100 yr). We examined whether these geographic differences in contact history and abundance may contribute to geographic differences in risk cue sensitivity, the amount of induced defense, and the scaling of trade-offs accompanying the induced defense,Risk cues from both crabs and damaged conspecifics induced the greatest increases in snail shell thickness, whereas exposure to just crab cues induced intermediate levels of thickening. Interestingly, our results suggest that the effects of risk cues are additive and that geographic differentiation in cue sensitivity only occurs in response to crab cues. While northern snails showed greater shell thickness plasticity in response to crab cues, there was no geographic differentiation in sensitivity to cues from damaged conspecifics. We also found that the scaling of trade-offs in body size vs. shell thickness was similar for both regions. This result contrasts with theory because one would expect the more intense selection regime caused by increased crab predation in the southern Gulf to diminish the impact of trade-offs on southern snails. However, this result is consistent with the hypotheses that (1) trade-offs in body size are likely mediated by architectural constraints imposed by the shell and (2) circumventing these constraints via changes in shell shape would likely result in a shell that is more vulnerable to crab predation. Analysis of aperture area and spire height for field populations revealed no geographic differentiation in aperture area, but taller spires in northern snails. Hence, more intense selection via crab predation in the southern Gulf may prevent changes in shell shape that reduce the impact of trade-offs. Finally, despite the large trade-offs accompanying increases in shell thickness, our study suggests that the functional value of increased shell strength in reducing vulnerability to crab predation outweighs these costs.																				WOS:000176400800018		J	Sebastian, CR; Steffani, CN; Branch, GM								Homing and movement patterns of a South African limpet Scutellastra argenvillei in an area invaded by an alien mussel Mytilus galloprovincialis								MARINE ECOLOGY PROGRESS SERIES				243				111	122					2002	2002	Over the last three decades, the Mediterranean mussel Mytilus galloprovincialis has invaded rocky shores on the west coast of southern Africa, and now makes up 74 % of intertidal mussel biomass. It competes directly with an abundant indigenous limpet, Scutellastra argenvillei, which attains high densities and biomass due to collective feeding on kelp. This competition has reduced the limpet's access to kelp, and dense aggregations of the limpets are now found only in small patches (termed 'established patches') that are remnants of the previous limpet belt. Lower densities of the limpets occur on mussel beds or in patches cleared of mussels by wave action ('cleared patches'). We investigated the effects of Mytilus encroachment on the movement patterns of S. argenvillei by comparing its homing and movements in these 3 situations. Short-term (12 h) homing frequency was similar on established patches (86.5 %) and newly created cleared patches (81.3 %) but significantly less on the mussel bed (60.4 %). On a monthly basis, homing frequency was lower, but significantly different in all 3 habitats (51.0, 29.2 and 10.9 %, respectively). Distances moved did not differ between habitats during the 12 h observations, but on a monthly basis were significantly greater on the mussel bed than in the other 2 habitats. There were no significant differences between the distances moved by juveniles versus adults for either 12 h or 1 mo periods. Small limpets on mussel beds frequently moved into cleared patches (29.8 %) while other limpets virtually never changed habitats. Mytilus encroachment has thus increased the mobility and reduced the homing frequency of S. argenvillei, probably because it limits access to kelp and increases dependency on alternative food sources. These changes in behaviour are associated with radical reductions' of the density and mean size of S. argenvillei in areas dominated by M galloprovincialis. Individuals that survive on the secondary substratum provided by mussels are all small and sexually immature. M galloprovincialis has thus had an impact on both the behaviour and population dynamics of S. argenvillei, with considerable implications for the proposed commercial harvesting of S. argenvillei.																				WOS:000179689200010		J	Tarr, Robert J. Q.								The South African abalone (Haliotis midae) fishery: A decade of challenges and change								Canadian Special Publication of Fisheries and Aquatic Sciences				130				32	40					2000	2000	The South African abalone, Haliotis midae, fishery is now 50 years old. The commercial sector has recently been consolidated into one category "rights holders," who may both dive and market their catch. A new overall total allowable catch (TAC) of 820 t (whole mass in shell) has been initiated. This includes a commercial TAC of 523 t, a new "subsistence" TAC of 138.5 t, and a recreational TAC of 158.5 t. Poaching is a major problem with a high proportion of sublegal-sized abalone being taken. This has resulted in serial reductions in TAC in one zone from 150 to 15 t. Intensive fishery-independent diving surveys are underway. Co-management and ranching pilot projects have been initiated. Movement of rock lobster, Jasus lalandii, into two of the major TAC zones has interrupted the normal recruitment cycle of H. midae due to lobster predation on sea urchins, Parechinus angulosus, which juvenile abalone depend on for protection. Due to the combined effect of poaching and ecological changes, the prognosis for the resource is now poor, with future reductions in TAC likely.																				BCI:BCI200200603606		J	Hayakaze, E; Chiba, S								Historical and ontogenetic changes in shell width and shape of land snails on the island of Kikai								AMERICAN MALACOLOGICAL BULLETIN				15	1			75	82					1999	1999	Patterns of change in shell width over a period of 35,000 years are documented in three fossil land snail species, Euhadra pachya (Pilsbry, Phaeohelix phaeogramma (Ancey), and Coniglobus mercatorius daemonorus (Pilsbry) on the island of Kikai in the Ryu-kyu Islands of the southwest part of Japan. The shell width of these species fluctuated through time, and the patterns were mostly synchronized among the three species. The temporal variations in shell width among fossil populations were far larger than geographical variations in shell width among modem populations. Since Kikai Island has been isolated from the other islands in the region, these morphological changes are regarded as genuine changes that have occurred within the island. The temporal changes in width were accompanied by distinct changes in spire indexj (height/width) within a single species. The patterns of change in width are correlated with the pattern of change in the climate since 35 Ka (35,000 years ago).																				WOS:000083593900007		J	DeWolf, H; Backeljau, T; Medeiros, R; Verhagen, R								Microgeographical shell variation in Littorina striata, a planktonic developing periwinkle								MARINE BIOLOGY				129	2			331	342					AUG 1997	1997	Littorina striata is a strictly Macaronesian, intertidal periwinkle with planktonic development. The species produces both nodulose and smooth shells, which co-occur at Ilheu de Vila Franca do Campo, a drowned crater situated about 1000 m off the south coast of Sao Miguel, Azores. The present work describes and analyzes the shell variation, temporal change and ecological distribution of the two shell types at this crater over a 3-year period. Nodulose shells were more common in the sheltered lagoon inside the crater, while smooth specimens dominated the outside of the wave-exposed crater. Moreover, nodulose specimens were smaller and weighed less compared to smooth ones. However, regardless of morphotype, shells from the lagoon had a smaller aperture and were less globose than those from the outside. Within an exposure regime, smooth specimens had a larger aperture. These patterns remained constant over time. They are tentatively interpreted as functional adaptations to thermal stress and wave exposure. The mechanisms that maintain these patterns are still unknown. Yet, aperture height of specimens transplanted from the lagoon to the outside increased markedly over a period of 5 months, whereas no comparable changes were observed in other experimental groups (i.e. transplanted from the outside into gr the lagoon, transplanted within the outside and transplanted within the lagoon; the latter two transplant groups being the blancos). This suggests that at least the aperture size in L. striata may be an ecophenotypically plastic trait.																				WOS:A1997XW28500013		J	Noda, T								Temporal changes in secondary production of a population of the subtidal sand snail Umbonium costatum in Hakodate Bay, northern Japan: Importance of annual change in age structure								JOURNAL OF SEA RESEARCH				37	1-2			145	152		10.1016/S1385-1101(97)00006-3			MAY 1997	1997	Year-to-year changes in age structure, biomass (B), annual secondary production (P) and P/(B) over bar ratio are described of a population of the subtidal snail Umbonium costatum in Hakodate Bay, northern Japan, during a 6-y period (1982-1988). Population structure and values of biomass and production were highly variable from year to year; the ranges of the annual mean biomass, annual production and PIE ratio were 3.71-9.22 g dry tissue m(-2), 1.01-4.92 g dry tissue m(-2) y(-1) and 0.13-1.33 y(-1), respectively. Change in the age structure was the most important single factor affecting temporal changes in annual production in this population. The annual production of the population was high when young individuals, which have a small body size and high growth rate, dominated the population. While annual P/(B) over bar ratios in 1983 and 1984 fell within the range of values reported for various other gastropods, those in 1985, 1986, 1987 and 1988 were markedly lower, if the relation between the population P/(B) over bar ratio and life span is taken into account. This demonstrates that production estimates from annual biomass and life-span values may lead to incorrect results in a recruitment-limited population.																				WOS:A1997XE26600012		J	GOULD, SJ								A DEVELOPMENTAL CONSTRAINT IN CERION, WITH COMMENTS ON THE DEFINITION AND INTERPRETATION OF CONSTRAINT IN EVOLUTION								EVOLUTION				43	3			516	539		10.2307/2409056			MAY 1989	1989																					WOS:A1989U611400003		J	KENT, BW								NATURAL-HISTORY OBSERVATIONS ON THE BUSYCONINE WHELKS BUSYCON-CONTRARIUM (CONRAD) AND BUSYCOTYPUS-SPIRATUM (LAMARCK)								JOURNAL OF MOLLUSCAN STUDIES				49	APR			37	42					1983	1983																					WOS:A1983QW58100007		J	VERMEIJ, GJ								ENVIRONMENTAL-CHANGE AND THE EVOLUTIONARY HISTORY OF THE PERIWINKLE (LITTORINA-LITTOREA) IN NORTH-AMERICA								EVOLUTION				36	3			561	580		10.2307/2408101			1982	1982																					WOS:A1982NW50700011		S	SCHELTEMA R S								DISPERSAL OF PELAGIC LARVAE AND THE ZOO GEOGRAPHY OF TERTIARY MARINE BENTHIC GASTROPODS								GRAY, J. AND A. J. BOUCOT (ED.). PROCEEDINGS OF THE ANNUAL BIOLOGY COLLOQUIUM OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY, VOL. 37. HISTORICAL BIOGEOGRAPHY, PLATE TECTONICS, AND THE CHANGING ENVIRONMENT; CORVALLIS, OREG., USA, 1976. XII+500P. OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY PRESS: CORVALLIS, OREG., USA. ILLUS. MAPS		Proceedings of the Annual Biology Colloquium (Oregon State University)						P391	398					1979 (RECD. 1980)	1979																					BCI:BCI198019026093		J	MONAKOV, AV								REVIEW OF STUDIES ON FEEDING OF AQUATIC INVERTEBRATES CONDUCTED AT INSTITUTE OF BIOLOGY OF INLAND WATERS, ACADEMY OF SCIENCE, USSR								JOURNAL OF THE FISHERIES RESEARCH BOARD OF CANADA				29	4			363	&					1972	1972																					WOS:A1972M275300003		